Mary Ware Dennett Case Collection
Mary Ware Dennett Case Collection
1919-1930
1927-1930
1 linear foot
Mss.arc
New York Academy of Medicine Library. Rare Book Room.
Historical Note
Mary Ware Dennett (1872-1947) was a birth control and sex education advocate. She was prosecuted in the late 1920s for sending her pamphlet, The Sex Side of Life, through the mail. Originally written for her sons, The Sex Side of Life was printed in The Medical Review of Reviews in 1918 and subsequently published and distributed in pamphlet form. The U.S. Post Office declared the pamphlet was obscene in 1922 and prohibited its distribution though the mail. Dennett continued to issue it that way and, in 1928, she was indicted under the 1873 Comstock Law and found guilty. A Mary Ware Dennett Defense Committee was organized under the American Civil Liberties Union to aid in her appeal, and Robert L. Dickinson was among her supporters. Her conviction was reversed by the Circuit Court of Appeals in 1930.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of copies of The Sex Side of Life, correspondence, clippings, printed matter, typed and manuscript notes, and the Appellant's Brief from the U.S. vs. Mary Ware Dennett case. The correspondence in this collection is largely to or from Robert L. Dickinson and his associates; correspondence and notes generated by Dickinson and his associates are carbon copies. There are also several instances of typed copies of others' letters.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Censorship -- United States.; Obscenity (Law) -- United States.; Sex instruction for childern.; Bryant, Louise Stevens, 1885-1956.; Dennett, Mary Ware, 1872-1947.; Dickinson, Robert Latou, 1861-1950.; American Civil Liberties Union.
Container List
  - The Sex Side of Life: An Explanation for Young People, 1919, 1928, 1928. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mary Ware Dennett Correspondence, 1927-1930. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Robert Dickinson and Associates Correspondence, 1927-1930. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mary Ware Dennett Defense Committee Correspondence, 1929-1930. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, undated, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mary Ware Dennett Defense Committee Documents, undated; 1929-1930. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, undated, 1929-1930. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Documents and Notes, undated, 1929. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Maydwell School: Human Engineering and Brochures, undated, 1928. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - United States of America against Mary Ware Dennett, Appellant's Brief. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Original documents in sealed wrappers., Please use archival copies! (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Original documents in sealed wrappers., Please use archival copies! (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Original documents in sealed wrappers., Please use archival copies! (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Original documents in sealed wrappers., Please use archival copies! (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Original documents in sealed wrappers., Please use archival copies! (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Original documents in sealed wrappers., Please use archival copies! (Box 1, Folder 16)
Due to physical condition of the carbon copies and clippings, these materials may not be handled and have been housed in sealed protective wrappers. Archival photocopies are provided for use.